As we just saw, local averaging has some very interesting mathematical properties.
正如刚才看到的 局部平均有着某种非常有趣的数学特性
It's a very simple operation as well and is very useful as we saw a few examples
同时这个操作很简单 从之前的例子可以看到这很有用
before. But we have also observed that it can
但是我们同时也看到 这会导致
blur the information in the image, it can blur the edges.
图像中的内容变模糊 边缘变模糊
So, how do we solve that? We have a number of different directions
所以 我们该怎么解决这个问题呢？ 我们有几种思路
to go. One is to basically replace this local
一种是用不同的局部运算来代替局部平均
averaging by a different local operation and we're going to see that very soon.
这个我们稍后可以看到
The other is, we may ask ourself, are we only limited to average in the local
而另外一种是这样的 我们可以先问问自己 我们只局限于对局部邻域求平均吗？
neighborhood? Maybe we can do a smarter average.
或许我们可以选择一个更好的求平均的方法
Remember that averaging is like a heat flow.
记住平均就像热量的流动
So, shall we basically average between a very hot pixel and a very cold pixel or
那么我们应该是在最大和最小的像素值之间取平均
shall we try only to average between pixels that are similar and try to stop
还是只对相似的像素点求平均
averaging pixels that are very different. And that's, a very interesting concept
并且不对相差很大的像素点求平均 这是一个非常有趣的想法
that can actually be implementing a very, very variety of ways in a very different
我们可以用多种方法 用不同方式来实现它
number of directions. But let's just explain one which is
现在我们来介绍一个特别简洁的方法
extremely elegant. In part it's elegant because it's very
从某种程度上说它简洁是因为它很简单
simple and it's actually called non-local means.
它就是非局部均值算法
Instead of looking at averages in the local neighborhood, we're going to look
与在局部邻域求平均不同
at averages in the whole image. Let's see why we can do that and how we
我们将在整个图像中求平均 一起来看看为什么能这样做
do that. The idea is very simple.
以及如何才能做到这点 这个思路非常简单
Let's just observe this image. We actually see that images have
一起来观察下这幅图像 我们能看到图像里有重复的东西
repetition. Sometimes these are called
有时候这些被称为图像的自相似性
self-similarities. So for example, if we look at this local
例如 如果我们着眼于这个局部邻域
neighborhood, it's very similar to this local neighborhood, and very similar to
它与这一个局部邻域非常相似
this local neighborhood. We also observed that here this local
也跟这个局部邻域非常相似 我们同样可以观察到这里的这个局部邻域
neighborhood is very similar to this local neighborhood,
与这个局部邻域非常相似
even similar to this. They're far away, but they're very
甚至与这个也相似 虽然它们隔得很远 但是它们很相似
similar, the same here.
这里也是同样的道理
So, before, we were thinking about averaging only pixels inside here, maybe
因此 我们之前只平均这里的像素
we should actually average neighborhoods that are similar.
也许我们应该平均相似的局部邻域
Maybe we should average these three, so we can replace this pixel by certain
或者我们可以对这三个进行平均 这样我们可以用
relationship with others, but we should not mix this with these because the local
这几个相似的像素计算并代替这个像素 但是不能把这个与这些混在一起
neighborhoods are very different. So, the basic idea of non local means or
因为它们的局部邻域非常不一样 所以 非局部均值或者是非局部平均的
non local averaging is to try to average, try to enjoy the properties of averaging
基本思路是尝试去平均某些局部邻域 并利用它们的特性
but not restrict that to a local neighbourhood.
而不是限定在一个局部邻域里
So why are we doing that, and how are we doing that?
那么我们为什么要这么做 以及 我们该怎么做呢？
So, the basic idea is that if we assume that these are identical things,
基本的思想是如果我们假设这些是相同的东西
identical structures, but maybe with different noise.
有着相同的结构 但是或许有不同的噪声
Let's see the effects of that. Let's assume that we have a certain
一起来看看这种假设的效果 现在假设有某个像素P
pixel, lets call it P, that's what we observed.
它是我们观察到的像素
It's the clean pixel plus some noise. But the noise, basically is a random
它是无噪的像素和噪声相加的结果 而这个噪声是一个随机变量
variable, so it's always slightly different.
因此结果总会有稍稍的不同
So, we observed the pixel a number of times.
所以 我们可以多次观察这个像素
We observed one with a certain noise. We observe it again, same pixel,
我们观察到了 P1 叠加了某一噪声 我们再次观察同一像素
but with a different noise. And we can observe it multiple times,
但是叠加了不同的噪声 我们可以观察多次
let's say that we observe this n times, always the same pixel but with different
比如说观察了 N 次 每次都是相同的像素和不同的噪声
realizations of the noise. If we average all these,
如果我们把这些做个平均
we can easily show these are basically properties of signal analysis,
我们可以看到一些信号分析中的特性
that the noise goes down proportional the square of the number of times that we
噪声按照我们平均的数量成平方下降
average. So we are averaging always the same
也就是说 我们总是在平均相同的像素
pixels, the noise is the random variable,
而噪声是个随机变量
and basically, the noise goes down proportional to n^.
于是噪声以N的平方成比例下降
The more we average, the more we reduce noise.
我们对越多像素值求平均 噪声减少得越多
Of course, it's very important that we always average exactly the same pixel.
当然 很重要的一点是我们总是平均相同的像素
The noise is the only thing that changes. So this is one of the motivations of non
噪声是唯一改变的地方 所以这是非局部均值产生的一个原因
local means to say, okay maybe I can find repeated structures that are identical or
或许我可以找到一些相同的或者很相似的结构
at least very similar, the noise is different all around and I can reduce
它们的噪声都是不一样的
that noise by averaging just because of this.
但我可基于这些 利用均值来降低噪声
And the basic idea then, is to look for similar neighborhoods first and average
那么 基本思路就是 首先找相似的邻域 然后求平均值
them. So if I want to replace this pixel in the
如果我想替换中心的像素
center, here, I look at the neighborhood. I look for similar neighborhoods and I
可以根据这个邻域来寻找近似的邻域
replace the pixel by the center, by the average of the center of the similar
然后用近似邻域的中心像素的均值来替换它
neighborhoods. And how do I find similar neighborhoods?
那怎样寻找近似邻域呢？
So there's a whole literature on non local means,
有专门讨论非局部均值的文献
that basically includes two parts. How do I find similar neighborhoods?
其中包括两部分 第一部分是怎样找到相似邻域
That's the first part. Once I found them, how do I average them?
找出它们之后 第二部分就是如何求得均值
Do I weighted average them? Do I compute a different relationship between them?
这时可以采用加权平均处理它们 或者也可以推演出它们之间不同的关系
But once again, the simplest for both options is look for neighborhoods by
但总体最简单的做法是通过比较来寻找邻域
comparing, let's say, the mean square error between them and make sure that
比如 比较对象之间的均方误差 要确保它非常小
it's very small. That's a very, very simple operation.
这是非常简单的操作
You go around the image you look at neighborhoods, lets say 3x3 or 5x5 or
你可以用 3x3 或 5x5 或 7x7 的邻域来扫描整个图像
7x7. And you say, okay,
这样做就可以了
who is similar to this? You go to around.
扫描整个图像 看看哪些与这个相似
You find a set of them. You can include all of them.
你会找到一组邻域 你可以用所有这些邻域
You can include just the most similar ones.
你也可以只用最相似的一些邻域
Once you find them, you go into the center of every neighborhood,
你一旦找到它们 就可以利用每个邻域的中心像素
and lets say you average that, and you replace the pixel by the average.
用它们的均值来替换那个像素
Then, if you want to actually clean a pixel that is here, you look for similar
如果你想消除这个像素上的噪声
pixel, similar neighborhoods to what's running that pixel,
你可以寻找拥有这样像素的邻域
you go around the image, you find a few, and you replace this
通过扫描整个图像 你会找到一些邻域
pixel by the average of the centers of all the similar neighborhoods.
用这些近似邻域的中心像素的均值来替换这个像素
Once again, this is just one example. You could look for similar neighborhoods
再一次说明 这个只是一个例子 你可以用不同的方法寻找相似的邻域
in a different fashion. You could, actually, once you find them,
实际上 一旦你找到它们
instead of doing average do a weighted average or do other functions but the
除了计算均值 还可以计算加权平均值 或者用其它的函数关系进行计算
concept is always the same. Instead of just averaging to rep, instead
这些操作都是基于同样的概念的
of just averaging around the neighborhood to replace this pixel, we basically look
这与仅仅在邻域内计算均值并以此代替像素不同
all around the image for similar neighborhoods with some measure of
我们用一种方法去衡量相似性 在整个图像中寻找相似的邻域
similarity. And once we find them, we combine them
而一旦找到这些邻域 就可以结合它们
and in such a way we denoise the pixel base on the concept I just explained.
用刚才所讲的概念对这个像素降噪
This is an extremely similar operation. Once again, basically one or two common
这样的处理都很相似 比如在 MATLAB 里 一到两行的命令
lines in [INAUDIBLE] for example. You can actually perform this operation
就可以完成这个处理过程
an extremely, extremely powerful and has opened a lot of research, very modern
这样的处理非常有用 而且在最近几年里
research in image processing basically in the last couple of years.
图像处理领域中展开了很多这方面的研究 很前沿的研究
What we're going to do next is I'm going to actually run some of these examples on
接下来我准备用一些图片来做例子
real images. I'm going to be doing this on real time.
进行演示 我会实时处理这些图像
So, see you in the next video for that.
那么 下一个视频再见 // 果壳教育无边界字幕组 | Cynthy |  luoyetx | 小白_远游